Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
What day is today in the Omer עומר? Omer? 47? 46? Okay,
fine. I know Shavuos שבועות Shavuos is around the corner. 46th day
in the Omer עומר Omer and Daf Ches דף ח, Daf Ches,
and we pick up at the bottom of Daf Zayin Amud Beis
דף ז עמוד ב. Daf Zayin Amud Beis. As I mentioned, we
are in the middle of some another about another two dafs דפים
dafs that's going to be dealing with all this issue about about
about collecting for Nezikin נזיקין. Nezikin. You collect you you the the
person who's damaged, the Nizak ניזק, Nizak, if he's being paid with
land gets of the best land, Meitav Sadeihu מיטב שדהו. Meitav Sadeihu.
And we're figuring out sort of debate of Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yishmael רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. Is it the
best quality land of the Mazik מזיק, Mazik, the best quality land
of the Nizak ניזק? Nizak? And then we're going to be looking
today particularly also in terms of other people that have rights to
collect money and which quality of land they collect from. But the
question that we ended up with yesterday at the bottom of Zayin
Amud Beis דף ז עמוד ב Zayin Amud Beis is when you
say the best, Meitav מיטב Meitav of the Mazik מזיק, Mazik, do
you really mean the best that he has or do you mean
grade A quality as determined by some objective standard? Right? Now the
again, the scenario cannot be that he only has grade B and
lower, because then obviously what can he give him other than grade
B, other than the best that he has, right? But the issue
is let's say he has, you know, triple A, he has, you
know, a quality that's much high that's higher than the standard grade
A quality. In that scenario does he have to pay him with
grade A which is the best of the universal standard, or does
he have to pay with his best which is, you know, triple
A? So that is the question that the Gemara גמרא Gemara raised,
and the immediate answer it gave was since it says Meitav Sadeihu
מיטב שדהו, Meitav Sadeihu, clearly it means his best. Okay, so that's
where we pick up at the bottom of Zayin Amud Beis דף
ז עמוד ב. Zayin Amud Beis. And the Gemara גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Rachmana amar רחמנא אמר Rachmana amar the Torah תורה Torah says Meitav
Sadeihu מיטב שדהו, Meitav Sadeihu, his best land, v'at amarta b'shel olam
shamini ואת אמרת בשל עולם שמיני v'at amarta b'shel olam shamini and
you think that we would do it based on some universal standard?
Clearly we do it based on his best based on what is
his best. Okay, so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now we're going to see if that's really true. Eseiv איתיבי, Eseiv,
I'll ask you on this. Ein lo ela idis, kulam govin min
ha-idis אין לו אלא עידית כולם גובים מן העידית. Ein lo ela
idis, kulam govin min ha-idis. Now, the basic rule is, and we
sort of alluded not alluded like mentioned this in passing yesterday, that
the people what quality of land you collect depends on what type
of a
collection you're doing. If you're collecting for damages, it's Meitav מיטב. Meitav.
If you are collecting for repayment for a loan, you're a Baal
Chov בעל חוב, Baal Chov, then it's Beinonis בינונית, Beinonis, it's the
average quality. That basically is for like a balance. On the one
hand,
we don't we want to encourage people to lend money. So if
we're only going to let them collect from the lowest quality, why
they going to lend money? I mean it's pretty hard to want
to lend money you know in the Torah תורה Torah system anyway,
which is why the Torah תורה Torah considers lending money its primary
form of Tzedakah צדקה. Tzedakah. If you read the psukim פסוקים psukim
closely in the Torah תורה Torah you will realize that the Torah
תורה Torah never ever ever says you're supposed to actually give money
to a poor person. Okay, the gift to the poor are the
Leket לקט, Leket, Shichecha שכחה, Shichecha, Peah פאה, Peah, and the Maaser
Ani מעשר עני. Maaser Ani. When a poor person asks for money
the Torah תורה Torah says you're supposed to lend them money because
it is Tzedakah צדקה, Tzedakah, because the loans get because it's interest-free
and the loans get annulled if they don't get paid off in
a certain amount of time. So anyway, it's hard enough to lend
money to to have the right to be motivated enough to lend
money. Obviously you have a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah to do it because
it's hard. And Chazal חז"ל Chazal wanted to therefore not create any
obstacles so they did not say that you would only collect from
the lowest quality land. The reason that you don't collect from the
highest quality land is any guesses why you wouldn't collect from the
highest quality land?
Hard for the borrower and also because it'll be predatory lending. You
will lend money knowing a guy has might not be able to
pay up because you want to actually use it as an opportunity
to seize his land. Okay, so anyway so that's why that's why
the Baal Chov בעל חוב Baal Chov gets from the middle level.
And the Kesubah כתובה Kesubah when a woman comes to collect her
Kesubah כתובה, Kesubah, she gets from the lowest level land, from the
grade C quality, the Ziboris זיבורית, Ziboris, basically on the presumption that
we need more to encourage guys to get married than women to
get married.
But anyway that was a whole discussion from Masechet Kesubos מסכת כתובות.
Masechet Kesubos. So those are the three qualities. Nezikin נזיקין Nezikin idis
עידית, idis, grade A; Baal Chov בעל חוב Baal Chov Beinonis בינונית,
Beinonis, grade B; Kesubas Ishah כתובת אשה Kesubas Ishah Ziboris זיבורית, Ziboris,
grade C. So let's take a look now at the Braitah ברייתא.
Braitah. Okay so the Braitah ברייתא Braitah says, Eseiv איתיבי: Eseiv: Ein
lo ela idis, kulam govin min ha-idis אין לו אלא עידית כולם
גובים מן העידית, Ein lo ela idis, kulam govin min ha-idis, if
the person only has a grade A quality. Kulam כולם, Kulam, all
three of these people now are coming to him to get paid,
the wife he divorced, the person whose car he damaged, and the
guy who he borrowed money from. What? Bad day. They're all coming
to collect from him
and he only has grade A land. So what else is he
going to do? Kulam govin min ha-idis כולם גובים מן העידית, Kulam
govin min ha-idis, they all collect from the grade A. They're all
coming to collect from him, and he only has Grade A land.
So what else is he going to do? כולם גובין מן העידית.
Kulam govin min ha-idit. They all collect from Grade A. בינונית. Beinonit.
If he only has Grade B, again bottom of ז׳ עמוד ב׳,
Zayin amud bet, three-four lines from the bottom. If he only has
Grade B, כולם גובין בינונית, Kulam govin beinonit, they all collect Grade
B. זיבורית. Ziborit. If he only has Grade C, כולם גובין זיבורית,
Kulam govin ziborit, they all collect Grade C. That was the easy
part, okay? Now, that's all the lead-up for the next line. היו
לו עידית ובינונית וזיבורית. Hayu lo idit u-veinonit v-ziborit.
He's got Grade A, B, and C, and presumably enough of each
quantity. So נזיקין בעידית ובעל חוב בבינונית וכתובת אשה
בזיבורית. Nizikin b-idit u-ba'al chov b-veinonit u-ktuvat isha b-ziborit. Like I said,
people that are collecting damages Grade A, creditors Grade B, כתובה ktuva
Grade C. עידית ובינונית. Idit u-veinonit. Now, let's say he only has
A and B. So נזיקין בעידית, nizikin b-idit,
the guy collecting damages, he has first rights to the עידית, idit,
he's entitled to that. ובעל חוב וכתובת אשה בבינונית. U-ba'al chov v-ktuvat
isha b-veinonit.
Now the בעל חוב ba'al chov is entitled to the בינונית. beinonit.
So this is an easy one, right? The כתובת אשה ktuvat isha
gets an upgrade. He can't give his divorced wife זיבורית, ziborit, he
only has בינונית, beinonit, she gets an upgrade. Okay, that was an
easy one. בינונית וזיבורית. Beinonit v-ziborit. Now you have only Grade B
and Grade C. So כתובת אשה ובעל חוב ktuvat isha v-ba'al chov
are obvious, B and C. And what else are you going to
do with the נזיקין? nizikin? He's going to have to get downgraded,
no choice. נזיקין ובעל חוב בבינונית, Nizikin u-ba'al chov b-veinonit, so the
guys collecting damages and the creditor get Grade B. וכתובת אשה בזיבורית,
U-ktuvat isha b-ziborit, and the כתובת אשה ktuvat isha is Grade C.
There's like no choices in those things. Those are all pretty obvious.
Now, how about this? עידית וזיבורית. Idit v-ziborit. Let's say it's Grade
A and Grade C. Okay, so there, here there's a choice, right?
The נזיקין nizikin gets Grade A. The כתובת אשה ktuvat isha gets
Grade C, excuse me I meant. Does the בעל חוב ba'al chov
get an upgrade or a downgrade? Okay, so נזיקין בעידית. nizikin b-idit.
In this scenario, what does the בעל חוב ba'al chov get? There's
only A and C.
No, there's enough of each to pay, presumably he could collect, there's
enough left over עידית idit that the בעל חוב ba'al chov could
collect, enough left over זיבורית ziborit the בעל חוב ba'al chov could
collect. Which one does he have a right to? The person who's
paying up would rather pay Grade C.
But this is the same question as if there's only one person
בעל חוב ba'al chov and the guy has A and C.
That's true. That is true. Okay. Oh, but then it wouldn't be
so interesting. Okay, but you're right. Okay, so
נזיקין בעידית בעל חוב וכתובת אשה בזיבורית. nizikin b-idit ba'al chov v-ktuvat
isha b-ziborit. So for some reason, the בעל חוב ba'al chov here
gets downgraded, and we'll discuss a little bit why that is. Okay,
basically רש״י. Rashi. So if you take a look at רש״י, Rashi,
רש״י Rashi says, look at רש״י Rashi second line of רש״י Rashi
from the top, מדאורייתא בעל חוב בזיבורית. mi-d'oraita ba'al chov b-ziborit. רש״י
Rashi explains to you why the בעל חוב ba'al chov gets downgraded
because biblically he really is only entitled to זיבורית, ziborit, but come
on. רבנן הוא דתיקנו ליה בבינונית. Rabbanan hu d'tiknu leh b-veinonit. The
rabbis gave him Grade B משום נעילת דלת. mishum ne'ilat delet. They
didn't want to create obstacles for people to lend money. והיכא דלית
ליה בינונית לית ליה תקנתא. V-heikha d'leit leh beinonit leit leh takanta.
But if there's no Grade B, he goes back to the normal
rule, which is the Grade C. Okay, so בעל חוב ba'al chov
is the only one that you have the interesting question for, right?
Because he's the one that's in a position to get, like a
כתובת אשה, ktuvat isha, if there's no Grade C, of course she
can only get upgraded, she can't get downgraded. And נזיקין, nizikin, if
there's no Grade A, of course he's going to get downgraded. The
only person who's interesting is the בעל חוב, ba'al chov, who could
be in a middle position and you have to choose between upgrading
or downgrading, and the חידוש chiddush is you downgrade. Okay, that was
a pretty straightforward ברייתא. braita. I mean, let's see what the גמרא
Gemara has to say about this. ותני מיהא מציעא. U-tani miha metzia.
We nevertheless taught in the middle case, בינונית וזיבורית. beinonit v-ziborit. If
there's Grade B and Grade C, נזיקין ובעל חוב בבינונית, nizikin u-ba'al
chov b-veinonit, נזיקין nizikin and creditor get Grade B וכתובת אשה בזיבורית,
v-ktuvat isha b-ziborit, and the woman gets C. Again,
seems pretty obvious, what else are you going to do? Now, here's
a point though. ואי אמרת בשלו הן שמין, V-im amarta b'shelo hen
shamin, if you say you determine the grade subjectively, then nobody is
ever going to have only Grade B and Grade C. Because his
Grade B will always be Grade A, it'll always be his best.
Okay? You know, it's like you say to your kids like, you
know, well, okay, you got a bad grade, but as long as
you gave your best effort, if this is your best effort, okay
anyway. But okay, so his Grade B will always be a Grade
A. So let's take a look. ואי אמרת בשלו הן שמין, V-im
amarta b'shelo hen shamin, if you say that you assess it based
on his own
subjective what he personally has, תעשה בינונית שלו כעידית. ta'aseh beinonit shelo
ke-idit.
So then his Grade B is really Grade A. And therefore, נזיקין
nizikin is entitled to Grade A. And therefore, ידחה בעל חוב אצל
זיבורית. yidacheh ba'al chov etzel ziborit.
So נזיקין nizikin should have all of Grade A and the בעל
חוב ba'al chov should not be entitled to Grade A and he
should go down to זיבורית. ziborit. So you see clearly, you know,
we're talking about some universal standard.
So the גמרא Gemara says, which is true, so that's clearly פשט.
pshat. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. הכא במאי עסקינן. Hakha be-mai
askinan. How can we explain this here while the בעל חוב... בעל
חוב ba'al chov is and the נזיקין nezikin are equally entitled to
grade B? If that's all he has, why don't we just consider
that to be grade A? So הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan
כגון דאית ליה עידית ומכרה. kegon de-it lei idit u-machra.
Ah, because what he damaged this person, when or when he borrowed
the money let's say, he had grades A, B, and C and
he borrowed the money. So the בעל חוב, ba'al chov, since at
that stage there was A, B, and C, the בעל חוב ba'al
chov had a lien on the grade B land. He was entitled
to grade B. Then the guy before or after did some damages
and then the guy he damaged, who he damaged, is entitled to
the grade A land or whatever. Then he sold the grade A
property. Or let's say first he sold the grade A property and
then he damaged somebody. So at that stage, even though his grade
B has now become grade A because he sold off the grade
A, okay, the בעל חוב ba'al chov still had a prior right
to that. He doesn't lose his rights. Everybody get that? So if
he started with B and C, then B would essentially be A
and the בעל חוב ba'al chov if he borrowed money then, the
בעל חוב ba'al chov wouldn't have any rights to it. But he
started with A, B, and C and the בעל חוב ba'al chov
had rights to grade B. Then even after he got rid of
grade A, the בעל חוב ba'al chov still retained his rights to
grade B.
Okay? You have a lien on that property?
Yeah. What? You don't understand?
So alright, so the classification of types of land is completely subjective
to what the person has.
Right, that's בשלו הן שמין. bishlo hen shamin. Obviously, you cannot run
an efficient system this way, okay? I think we all intuitively understand
and hope that the גמרא Gemara is going to reject this possibility.
I will just tell you because Michael always wants to know how
we פוסק. pasken. The גמרא Gemara is not clear what it says
at the end and not to ruin it, but I'm going to
ruin it anyway. Take a look at this little תוספות. Tosefos. תוספות
Tosefos says, he says, where's the תוספות? Tosefos?
להוציא פחות שבכלים. le-hotzi pachas she-ba-kelim. If you look three lines at
the bottom of that תוספות, Tosefos, ונראה דהלכה דבשלו הן שמין דהכי
אית ליה לרב נחמן בכתובות. ve-nireh de-halacha di-bishlo hen shamin de-hachi is
lei le-Rav Nachman bi-Ksuvos. So תוספות Tosefos actually rule the subjective standard.
I think like it's besides that, it's such a hard rule in
the text that we have. It's like how are you really supposed
to run a system like that? But anyway, yes.
I mean I get that it's not efficient, but I'm, what I
thought just sounds like lien property, which sounds entirely inefficient to grade
B also, right? That like, I mean I have
to keep track of all those things, like once you have the
system worked out, you got the system worked out, like maybe right?
If we don't think it's ridiculous enough to share then why should
it be discovered?
Right, I mean one is record keeping, the other is like constantly
switching standards of which property you're entitled to.
Like keeping track of what
the person has and maybe you're right, at the time that the
debt is incurred, right, then you do an assessment and right. Okay,
I hear that. All right, so let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan כגון
דאית ליה עידית ומכרה. kegon de-it lei idit u-machra. So the reason
the בעל חוב ba'al chov is entitled to B, even though there's
only B and B should be A, is because he got, he
had his liens, the money was lent when there was an A
and that gave him rights to B and he doesn't lose those
rights to B. וכן אמר רב חסדא כגון דהוה ליה עידית ומכרה.
ve-chen amar Rav Chisda kegon de-hava lei idit u-machra. And that's also
explained that way. הכא נמי מסתברא, hacha nami mistabra, that actually makes
sense that that's what we're talking about. Why? מדקתני אחריתי, mi-de-katni achriti,
we've got another ברייתא. braita. בין עידית וזיבורית, bein idit ve-ziborit,
if you've got again this case of B and C, נזיקין בבינונית
בעל חוב וכתובת אשה בזיבורית. nezikin bi-venonit ba'al chov u-ksuvas isha bi-ziborit.
We actually have a contradiction of the ברייתות. braitos. Okay, I think
I've got to write this down.
You have grade B and grade C, okay? Our ברייתא braita teaches
נזיקין nezikin
and
בעל חוב ba'al chov get grade B and כתובת אשה ksuvas isha
gets grade C. Okay, we have another ברייתא braita that teaches in
this case, and we'll do it on this side, B and C,
that says that נזיקין nezikin gets that and בעל חוב ba'al chov
and כתובת אשה ksuvas isha get grade C. Okay, so the question
is the בעל חוב. ba'al chov. We'll put the בעל חוב ba'al
chov in the middle. Okay,
so we have one ברייתא braita that says that and one ברייתא
braita that says that. What's
the?
You want the, you want the other arrow red?
That's true, maybe that'll make it clearer. All right, anyway, so,
so why are these ברייתות braitos disagreeing? Why is the בעל חוב
ba'al chov in one case getting B and one case getting C?
So let's take a look. So we've explained that this case, right,
the reason the בעל חוב ba'al chov is entitled to B, why
do we explain? We said it's בשלו הן שמין, bishlo hen shamin,
that really it's subjective, so B is really A, and the real
reason, and that's why נזיקין, nezikin, you know, would obviously get it,
that's the best, and the only reason he's entitled to A is
because there had been an A that had been sold off. So
since there was an A that had been sold, that when the
money was... When the loan was taken out, there was an A
that gave him rights, he doesn't lose those rights. So now we
can understand why here he doesn't get B, because if there was
never an A, if you started with this, and we say בשלו
יהא שמין, beshelo yehei shamin, then B is going to have been
an A. There was never another A, and the בעל חוב ba'al
chov would always have only been entitled to C.
Is that clear? Yeah, exactly. Is this confusing? Drawing on the board?
Okay. If the board confuses you, ignore it. And let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. קשיא אהדדי, kashya ahadadi, we have
a contradiction: Does the בעל חוב ba'al chov get B or C?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא לאו שמע מינה כאן שעשאה עידית
ומכרה. ela lav shma mina kan she-asa'ah idit u-machrah. In one case,
he gets B because it's all going to be a subjective standard.
There had been an A, which therefore entitled him to the B,
and then the A was sold off. So that's why he remains
entitled to the B. כאן שלא עשאה עידית ומכרה. kan shelo asa'ah
idit u-machrah. The other case is there had never been an A.
There was only a B and a C. And in that case,
since it's a subjective standard,
he's not entitled to the B. And he's therefore, that's the case
if there was never an A and it's subjective, then this is
the A and he was always only entitled to the C. So
that explains how these ברייתות braitot resolve if you assume בשלו יהא
שמין, beshelo yehei shamin, it's subjective, and then it'll make a difference
whether there had been an A or not, and you know, whether
the A had been there and been sold off. Okay, yes?
And you still, though, you could argue that he should get the
בינונית beinonit because of נעילת דלת. neilat delet.
But that's the point. If there is no בינונית, beinonit, that's what
we taught at the top of the דף, daf, then we go
back to the דאורייתא. d'oraita. So if you have a subjective standard,
there's no בינונית. beinonit. This becomes an A, and then you're back
to an A and a C scenario.
If you look at it subjectively, then this is an A and
this is a C, so he gets the C. The only reason
here this remains a B is because there had been an A.
Right, it can't be no בינונית beinonit if it's subjective.
Yeah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so that's how we've resolved it. Now we're going to give
two other ways of resolving this contradiction in the ברייתות braitot based
on this issue of בשלו, בשל עולם, beshelo, beshel olam, etc. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you want I could say, אידי ואידי
שלא עשאה עידית ומכרה, idi ve-idi shelo asa'ah idit u-machrah, we're not
dealing with that scenario about having had עידית. idit. Forget that. ולא
קשיא, velo kashya, הא דשוייה בינונית שלו כעידית דעלמא והא דלא שווייה
בינונית שלו כעידית דעלמא. ha deshavia beinonit shelo k-idit d'alma ve-ha delo
shavia beinonit shelo k-idit d'alma. The difference is that we're really talking
about בשל עולם הם שמין. beshel olam hem shamin. Okay, we can
resolve this if we understand that it means בשל עולם הם שמין.
beshel olam hem shamin. Why? Because when it says בינונית, beinonit, okay,
it doesn't really mean בינונית. beinonit. It's his בינונית. beinonit. Of course
it's funny, but his בינונית beinonit also is, I don't know, it's
hard to explain this. But anyway, it says what it really means
is that this בינונית beinonit is, in this case, this בינונית beinonit
is worth, is really grade A as far as the rest of
the world is concerned. So if it's grade A, בעל חוב ba'al
chov isn't entitled. In this case, his בינונית beinonit is a standard
grade B. So therefore, if it's a standard grade B, he is
entitled to it. Which basically means you can resolve these ברייתות braitot
assuming בשלו הם שמין beshelo hem shamin and you can resolve these
ברייתות braitot assuming בשל עולם הם שמין. beshel olam hem shamin. Okay.
ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you want you can say, אידי ואידי
דהוה בינונית שלו כבינונית דעלמא. idi ve-idi d-hava beinonit shelo k-beinonit d'alma.
His grade B is the world's grade B. Okay.
והכא בהא פליגי, ve-hacha be-ha paligi, maybe this is exactly the debate
of these two ברייתות. braitot. מר סבר בשלו הם שמין ומר סבר
בשל עולם הם שמין. mar savar beshelo hem shamin u-mar savar beshel
olam hem shamin. That's the best. Okay, this is exactly the debate.
If you say you go בשל עולם, beshel olam, then the בעל
חוב ba'al chov gets grade B, right? If you say you go
בשלו, beshelo, then the grade B is a grade A, and the
בעל חוב ba'al chov does not get it. So the easiest way
to resolve these ברייתות, braitot, I don't know how easy, it's easiest
given that we framed this question,
not resolve, you're saying it's a מחלוקת. machloket.
Right, it's a מחלוקת, machloket, thank you, to explain these ברייתות braitot
right, is to say that, well, if we start by saying, oh,
this is a קשיא kashya according to the one that says בשלו
הם שמין, beshelo hem shamin, and the answer is you're right, this
ברייתא braita assumes בשל עולם הם שמין. beshel olam hem shamin. And
because it's בשל עולם, beshel olam, the בעל חוב ba'al chov is
entitled to grade B. הא, ha, here we have a ברייתא braita
that says he's not entitled to grade B. You know why? This
ברייתא braita assumes בשלו הם שמין. beshelo hem shamin. So the grade
B is a grade A and therefore the בעל חוב ba'al chov
is not entitled to it. Nice way of dealing with the ברייתות,
braitot, the ברייתות braitot split exactly along the lines of the issue
that we have framed. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
רבינא אמר בדאולא פליגי. Ravina amar bid-Ula paligi. No, no, no, you
know what these ברייתות braitot debate? They debate עולא's Ula teaching, which
is what רש"י Rashi already sort of told us about. דאמר עולא,
d-amar Ula, דבר תורה, dvar Torah, from the Torah's perspective, בעל חוב
בזיבורית. ba'al chov be-ziborit. The בעל חוב ba'al chov really is only
entitled to the lowest quality. שנאמר, shene'emar, בחוץ תעמוד, bachutz ta'amod, you
shall stand outside if you have a loan to collect from somebody,
והאיש אשר אתה נושה בו, ve-ha'ish asher ata nosheh vo, the man
that you have a sort of that you are demanding money against,
יוציא אליך את העבוט החוצה, yotzi eleicha et ha-avot hachutza, will bring
to you the collateral to the outside. So it means It's his
initiative, his decision what to give you, what to bring to you.
So if it's his decision, מה דרכו, Mah Darko, מה דרכו של
אדם להוציא, Mah Darko Shel Adam Lehotzi, what is he going to
bring out לחוץ פחות שבכלים? Lachutz Pachot She'bekeilim? He'll give you the
worst of his vessels. So therefore you see that you're really only
entitled to the worst. OK, A: that's collateral, it's not necessarily payment,
although collateral could become payment, but B: תוספות Tosfos says, I don't
understand, we just said a דף Daf ago that all cattle is
considered to be good quality and it's not the same as land.
So yeah, תוספות'ס Tosfos's question is better than the answer.
OK, let's look at
תוספות. Tosfos. להוציא פחות שבכלים, Lehotzi Pachot She'bekeilim, תוספות Tosfos says, ואם
תאמר אפילו פחות שבכלים מיטב הוא כדאמרן לעיל כל מילי מיטב הוא,
Ve'im Tomar Afilu Pachot She'bekeilim Meitav Hu Ke'damran Le'eil Kol Mili Meitav
Hu, ויש לומר כשמוציא כלים דרכו להוציא הגרוע, Veyesh Lomar Keshe'motzi Keilim
Darko Lehotzi Ha'garua, וכשמוציא קרקע נמי דרכו להוציא זיבורית. U'keshe'motzi Karka Nami
Darko Lehotzi Ziborit. So since it's basically saying it's his initiative, we're
saying, no, the scenario in the תורה Torah is he's bringing you
out some, some like, you know, I don't know, chamber pot or
something. OK, but what it tells you is it's his initiative what
to pay you with. OK, so if it's his initiative what to
pay you with, his decision, when it comes to land also, you'll
only get Grade C. So that's what he says, בעל חוב Ba'al
Chov only gets Grade C. ומה טעם אמרו בעל חוב בבינונית? U'mah
Ta'am Amru Ba'al Chov Bi'veinonit? Why do they say he gets Grade
B? כדי שלא תנעל דלת בפני לווין, Kedei Shelo Tin'al Delet Bifnei
Lovin, you shouldn't lock the door in the face of people who
want, who would be prepared to lend money. מר איתא תקנתא דעולא,
Mar Ita Takanta De'ula, one holds of עולא'ס Ula's תקנה Takana that
we start with Grade B, ומר ליתא תקנתא דעולא, U'mar Leita Takanta
De'ula, the other one says that actually we never made the תקנה.
Takana. Generally says that a בעל חוב Ba'al Chov only gets זיבורית,
Ziborit, which is now it's much less interesting. So meaning we say,
we would say,
בשל עולם הן שמין, Beshel Olam Hen Shamin, OK, so if it's
בשל עולם הן שמין, Beshel Olam Hen Shamin, this one says a
בעל חוב Ba'al Chov gets Grade B, and why does this one
say a בעל חוב Ba'al Chov gets Grade C? Because this one
feels that we don't make a תקנה, Takana, we leave the בעל
חוב Ba'al Chov at the דאורייתא De'oraisa level and therefore he only
gets the זיבורית. Ziborit. Of course if that's true, why did we
tell you this, you know, complicated scenario? Just tell me as a
general principle a בעל חוב Ba'al Chov gets Grade C. So תוספות
Tosfos says it doesn't mean he doesn't hold of the תקנה Takana
of עולא. Ula. It means when there's any competition with other people
who are owed money, we would go, we would immediately drop him
back, OK, down to sort of this level. So therefore the question
basically would be if you want to frame it another way, we
would say בשל עולם, Beshel Olam, so you understand why Grade B,
but at what stage are we ready to downgrade the בעל חוב?
Ba'al Chov? And the other approach holds, no, no, no, we're much
more ready to downgrade the בעל חוב Ba'al Chov if there's any
type of competition around who gets which land. Yes, Charlie.
Back to the case where I used to have Grade A land
and now I've sold it. If I lend you money with your
property as collateral, right, and I register the lien, right, you can't
sell it without my...
yeah, now you're talking about secularly. Yeah, that's not true in הלכה.
Halacha. I can sell it but then you can collect it from
the person I sold it to.
Yeah, because he has a claim to the subsequent purchase?
Yes, yes. That's the whole, and that's like a whole major section
in ש"ס Shas is about that, that you then, you know, exercise
your lien when it's in a certain other person's hand and then
that person you sold it to, if he bought it with insurance,
with אחריות, Achrayut, can come back to you to get repaid and
so we're actually going to have a case like that coming up.
Yeah.
So תוספות'ס Tosfos's question doesn't apply as much if we go by
בשל עולם, Beshel Olam, right? That's an easier read because then... why?
...it's A, C, yeah, and then so the נפקא מינה Nafka Mina
is do you upgrade him to A because...
right, but that doesn't seem... so that sort of seems to be
the earlier אוקימתא, Ukimta, but this אוקימתא Ukimta that's framed it all
in עולא, Ula, right, doesn't seem to be about that. If that
was the way, if it was because we do בשל עולם הן
שמין, Beshel Olam Hen Shamin, you don't need to bring in the
עולא Ula issue, then that's, we've already said that that explains why
the בעל חוב Ba'al Chov gets Grade C.
But it doesn't explain why he gets C in the other case.
Right, right.
OK, I think we're just going to go back to the earlier
אוקימתות. Ukimtas. But alright, so let's take a look now at the
next topic. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, now because if you, I hope
you've been having fun until now because we're going to be doing
more of this. OK, so because we introduced the competition of the
בעל חוב Ba'al Chov and the כתובת אשה Kesuvat Ishah and the
נזיקין, Nezikin, we're going to continue to talk about scenarios and how
they sort of distribute the land amongst them. So let's take a
look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, or... מכר לאחד, Machar Le'echad,
so you had these three people coming against you, OK, your ex-wife
for her כתובה, Kesuvah, the guy whose car you rammed into, and
the guy who you borrowed $1,000 from. All three in court? Yeah.
Now, so we've already decided that if you have three grades of
property, they get distributed accordingly. But what I did here, exactly as
you were asking, what I did was is I just sold all
my property. OK, go bother people I sold it to. OK, so
if I sold all my property, my A, B, and C property
to somebody, או לשלושה בני אדם, O Le'shlosha Bnei Adam, or I
sold it to three people, ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי. Levi.
או לשלושה בני אדם o lishlosha bnei adam or I sold it
to three people, ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי, Levi, כאחד ke'echad
at the same time, which means basically on the same day, כולם
נכנסו תחת הבעלים. kulam nichnesu tachat habaalim.
So they all take my place and the נזיקין nezikin would collect
from the guy who has grade A and the בעל חוב baal
chov from the guy who has grade B and the כתובת אשה
kesubas isha from the guy who has grade C. Wait, did he
pay them
from proceeds from the sale?
Well,
that's a good point. They actually could come to me first, but
let's say I spent the cash in the interim. Okay, so
now, where were we? Okay, כולם נכנסו תחת הבעלים. kulam nichnesu tachat
habaalim. בזה אחר זה. beze achar ze. Now, let's say I sold
my property to three people, but on different days. Now, כולם גובים
מן האחרון. kulam govin min ha'acharon. Then whatever order I sold it
to—and for—it's
the same day?
The same day is considered the same time, because unless you're in
ירושלים Yerushalayim when they put the hour in the שטר, shtar, otherwise
it's all considered to be the same time. Now, let's make life
simple. I only sold to each person, I sold only one quality
of land. Okay, so I sold to three people, okay, three people.
Now, and one guy I sold A, one guy B, one guy
C. Whoever was the last person who bought my land, whatever quality
it is, all three of my—the people I owe money to—collect from
that land.
Assuming he has enough to pay them all?
Assuming he has enough and—exactly, exactly. Okay. כולם גובים מן האחרון. kulam
govin min ha'acharon. אין לו, ein lo, if he doesn't have enough
to pay them all, גובה משלפניו, gove m'shelfanav, then they go to
the
guy after—the second I sold. ואם אין לו גובה משלפני פניו. v'im
ein lo gove m'shlifne fanav. If not, they go to the first
guy. And because that is the principle of, as Michael pointed out
with the—if you spent the cash, if I have the cash I
gotta pay with the cash. If I have property, you cannot go
to somebody who bought lean property from me before you go to
me. Okay. That person is like the last resort. He basically says,
the person who owes the money is the person who has primary
responsibility. And if he has any cash on hand or any property
on hand, he has to pay. You only get to go to
the person who purchased the property if the guy who owes you
money cannot pay. So that's why you have to go to the
last person. Because person one and person two will say, when we
bought our property, property that person three now owns was still under
the possession of the guy who owes money. So therefore that was
the property that all of the creditors, right, had rights to because
we were leaving that property behind. So therefore, when that property gets
sold to guy number three, everybody has to first go to guy
number three, because their rights got focused onto that last property. Okay.
Now, once guy three has given all his property away—or given all
the property away and there's still outstanding loans, then guy one can
say, ah, but you know, your rights first have to focus on
property number two, right? Because that was the one that when I
bought property number one, everybody would have collected from properties three and
two. So you can only come to me after you've exhausted your
claims on those properties.
Someone's getting an upgrade? What?
Or someone made a downgrade. Somebody's getting an upgrade or a downgrade,
right, exactly.
Could you argue the opposite? Couldn't you argue that you should collect
from guy number one first, closer
to the—thinking of it as, guy three came in and bought the
property from the guy. He knows that he's buying the last bit
of land, right? Like, he knows there's nothing else for people to
collect from. But guy one says, oh he has all this other
land, you know, they'll collect from him.
Right, he'll collect directly from him.
Exactly. Okay, so, okay,
so, מכרן לאחד. machran l'echad. Now, the גמרא's Gemara going to analyze
this. מכרן לאחד היכי דמי? machran l'echad heichi dami? When you sold
it to one person, what's the case? אי בבת אחת, ei b'vas
achas, if you sold all three grades to one person at one
time, השתא לשלושה, hashta lishlosha, when you sold it to three people
on
the same day, דאיכא למימר חד מינייהו קדים, d'ika l'meimar chad mineihu
kadim, and one of them did come before, I mean at least,
you know, an hour before the other guy, and nevertheless, אמרת כולם
נכנסו תחת הבעלים, amarta kulam nichnesu tachat habaalim,
that it plays out just like if the owner had it. You
know, we look at it all at the same day as the
same time. And the נזיקין nezikin go to A, בעל חוב baal
chov to B, and כתובה kesuba to C. So מכרן לאחד מבעיא?
machran l'echad mibaya? When you sell to one person, where it's literally
all taking effect at the same moment, of course he takes the
place of the בעלים. baalim. You don't have to tell me that
case. Of course, you know, you and I would just say fine,
the case of selling it to one person was obvious, it started
with that and then it said sold it to three people. But
the גמרא Gemara wants to make the case of one person a
חידוש. chiddush. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא פשיטא בזה אחר זה.
ela pshita beze achar ze. Here's the חידוש. chiddush. I sold my
land here, all these people I owe money to, I sold my
land here to Michael. And I sold this to Michael on three
different days. On day number one I sell Michael grade A. On
day number two I sell Michael grade B, and on day number
three I sell Michael grade C. Then my creditors all come to
Michael. Michael might want to say to them, hey, you all have
to collect from grade C. Because I bought grade A and grade
B first, so all of your rights were centered on grade C,
even though now I have all three of them. Okay, you gotta
all go to grade C. So that is a big חידוש, chiddush,
that they can say to him, no buddy, you have all three
grades, we're collecting the way we would collect. So let's take a
look. Someone's getting an upgra—
It's only because he has all of them from me, right, it's
only because he has all those properties and they're all from me,
right.
Not for debtor here. Right, so I think it's not a חידוש,
chidush, it's logical because the last land in your possession. Right. No.
Right, so you would think that therefore they all have to collect
from the last piece of property that Michael brought bought. But that's
not the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha is that the נזיקין nezikin
can collect from the grade A that he bought two weeks ago.
Right. Okay, so let's take a look. That's why you have LLCs
fine. So anyway, אי אפשר בזה אחר זה ומה ישנה שלושה דכל
חד וחד אמר ליה הנחתי לך מקום לגבות הימנו. ee efshar bezeh
achar zeh u-mah shanah shloshah dechol chad vechad amar lei hinachti lecha
makom ligvot heimenu.
Exactly as Jenna said, you see? I remember reading the Gemara, Jenna
exactly anticipated the articulation of why you have to buy get from
the last one first. Because every prior one says, I left over
property behind in the possession of the original guy, so so I
was protected. So you had property to collect from. You only come
to me after you've exhausted those claims. All right, that's why when
it's three different people at different days every you have to you're
forced to go to the last guy. So if that's true says
the גמרא, Gemara, so why not here why not here say the
same thing? היי נמי hai nami when Michael bought all three properties
on different days, נמי כל חד וחד לימא ליה הנחתי לך מקום
לגבות הימנו. nami kol chad vechad leima lei hinachti lecha makom ligvot
heimenu. Let Michael say to everybody even the נזיקין, nezikin, hey, I
left over the last piece of property so that you would collect
from that last piece and all of your claims are centered on
that last piece of property. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הכא
במאי עסקינן כגון שלקח עידית באחרונה. hacha bemai askinan kegon shelakach idit
ba-acharonah.
So the גמרא Gemara basically says, you know what, you're right. You're
totally right. Michael could say that. And even though he has all
three pieces of property, we would have to collect from the last
one. I'm the נזיקין, nezikin, Jenna's the one who I ran into
her car, so Jenna now, sorry Jenna. So Jenna now is going
to
collect forced to the last grade C because Michael said that was
the last piece of property I bought. All of your rights get
focused on the grade C land. אין הכי נמי ein hachi nami
says the גמרא, Gemara, though he has all three grades, he can
force the person to collect from the last one. So what is
the case that they would divide that they normally would divide between
A, B, and C?
Wait, I'm sorry, wait.
If I bought all of it anyway,
no, on separate days.
So the גמרא's Gemara saying actually is you know what, you're right.
If you buy it on separate days then everybody has to collect
from the last parcel assuming there's enough. Okay? So why would why
then did we say but that's not what we taught. We taught
that if Michael has all three properties they divide naturally between עידית
בינונית וזיבורית. idit beinonit ve-ziborit. Ah, that's a special case. That's the
case when Michael doesn't want them to collect from the last parcel.
The last parcel was the grade A. Okay? So it is not
in Michael's interest to have them collect from the last parcel. So
then Michael can say, you know what, even though I left over
that piece, I'm actually fine with you collecting from the earlier property
as well. So let's take a look. כגון שלקח עידית באחרונה. kegon
shelakach idit ba-acharonah. He collected he bought the grade A last. Okay?
ואמר רב ששת כגון שלקח עידית באחרונה. ve-amar Rav Sheshet kegon shelakach
idit ba-acharonah. So then the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if that's
true, why can't he divide them equally? אי הכי ee hachi says
the גמרא Gemara let's be consistent. ליתו כולהו וליגבו מעידית. leisu kulhu
veligvu mei-idit.
So fine, so if that was the last piece of property they
all have right to the grade A property. That was the last
one left over. Let everybody collect from the grade A. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. משום דאמר להו mishum de-amar lehu because Michael
will say to those to people who want to come collect from
the grade A: אי שתקיתו ושקליתו כדינייכו שקליתו. ee shatkitu ve-shaklitu kedineichu
shaklitu.
Look, here's your choice. Either shut up and get what you're deserving,
A, B, or C, okay? Now you say no, no, no, I
want
grade A that was the last one that was left over. ואי
לא מהדרנא שטרא דזיבורית למאריה ושקליתו כולכו מזיבורית. ve-ee lo mahadarna shtra
de-ziborit le-mareih ve-shaklitu kulchu mi-ziborit.
If you want no, if you if you do that you know
what I'm going to do? I'm just going to basically give the
זיבורית ziborit back to the original owner and then you'll all be
forced to get grade C. You're all coming to me because the
original owner has no property left. So I'm going to make you
guys a deal. Either we can agree you all want grade A
and in theory you really are entitled to grade A, it was
the last piece of property, but either you'll sort of go to
what you'll get what you sort of really deserve in terms of
the quality, and if not I'll just give the grade C. Right.
So Michael so so it could be what he's also saying is
like I'll burn the document and I'll deny that I ever bought
it. Now of course can you really make that claim because then
you'd be out the money. If I collect if if they collect
from you you could always come back to me. The גמרא's Gemara
not going to be thrilled with this answer, but that's at least
the answer for now. He's sort of he's threatening them, okay, that
I'm gonna stick you all with grade C if you don't play
my game. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ee hachi the
גמרא Gemara is not happy with it. If that's true says the
גמרא Gemara בניזיקין נמי נימא הכי. bi-nezikin nami neima hachi. So if
that's true, why does the נזיקין nezikin guy get grade A? Why
doesn't Michael just threaten everybody? So basically this is not הלכה Halacha
what we're saying. This is just manipulation and threats. So therefore if
Michael's threatening them, say to the נזיקין Nizikin guy, buddy listen, here's
your choice: either get grade D, okay, or I'm just gonna give
the- give grade C back to the owner and then you'll be
stuck with grade C, right? So because why not? I mean he
has the leverage, he has the manipulation. So obviously we're not talking
that that's what's going on, that he's just using his leverage. Okay
A, it'd be funny for us to be teaching that הלכה, Halacha,
and B because then you wouldn't- and secondly because then the עידית
Idis would not be getting grade A. He'd use his leverage to
have the greed-iest guy get- get grade B.
Against the laws anyway.
Well that's also what's not being explained, right? That's another question. You
could still make it a special case. If Michael- whether- he can't
always come back and collect from me, it depends if he basically
has אחריות, achrayus, if he did it with insurance or not. So
anyway, but let's not go there. The גמרא's Gemara not happy with
this answer. אלא, Ella, fine, forget that answer. הכא במאי עסקינן Hacha
bemai askinan what are we talking about? ביתמי דלאו בני פירעון נינהו
Byasmi delav bnei piron ninhu ושיעבודא אלי דידיה רמיא. v'shibuda alei didei
ramya. So what we're talking about is the following, is that the
person who- hold on, let me just double check רש״י Rashi make
sure I'm getting this right.
Ah, okay. So what we're talking about- oh no, the first thing
we have to explain before we explain why it's A, B, and
C is why this leverage doesn't work. Why doesn't this leverage work?
Why doesn't Michael sort of sit- use this threat of giving back
grade C and then I'm gonna force everybody to get grade B
or lower? So the answer is the guy he bought it from
is no longer alive. Okay? So if the guy he bought it
from is no longer alive, then if he winds up giving back
the grade
C to the orphans, then the creditors are not entitled to collect
the grade C from the orphans. It gets very complicated, but basically
when the guy died, the creditors have rights to any property that
the orphans inherited right now, any land property. But any property that
they get later, the guy doesn't have rights to- the creditors don't
have rights to. So if the guy that sold Michael the property
died and Michael gives the grade C back, the creditors don't have
rights to that grade C because it's new property that the orphans
took possession of. So because he- because these creditors will never be
able- even if he gives the property back- won't go to the
orphans, Michael has no leverage over the creditors. He can't make that
threat. Okay, fine. We've neutralized his threat, but we're still back to
our question. If Michael bought grade A at the end, why doesn't
everybody collect from grade A? Okay, everybody with me? We tried to
answer it by giving Michael some leverage and making a threat, we
said that's not the case. Fine, but why does everybody not collect
from grade A? Okay? So הכא במאי עסקינן ביתמי דלאו בני פירעון
נינהו Hacha bemai askinan byasmi delav bnei piron ninhu by orphans that
are not ones that these creditors can collect from, ושיעבודא דיליה אלי
דידיה
רמיא v'shibuda dilei alei didei ramya and therefore the lien are only
against Michael. They're never going to be able to get back from
the orphans. Is Michael the לוקח? lokeach? No, the- the guy who
owed all the money, the guy who sold all the property to
Michael. הלכך ליכא למימר הכי. Hilkach leka lemeimar hachi. Michael doesn't have
his threat. He can't say I'll give him back his grade C
and you'll all be forced here to do that. Okay, אלא משום
דאמר להו... Ella mishum de’amar lehu...
okay, but wonderful. He doesn't have the threat. Why doesn't everybody collect
from grade A if Michael bought grade A at the end? And
here is a straightforward answer to that. אלא משום דאמר להו... Ella
mishum de’amar lehu... טעמא מאי אמרו רבנן אין נפרעין מנכסים משועבדים במקום
שיש בני
חורין? Ta’ama mai amru Rabbanan ein nifrain minechasim meshubadim bemakom sheyesh bnei
chorin? What is it that- let's go back. Michael bought grade A
and B from me, okay, and he left grade- and he left
grade A. If the people came to collect at that stage... he
left grade- you- you- you bought grade A at the end. But
you first bought grade B and C from me, right? That's the
scenario, everybody right- remember that? That's the scenario. You bought grade B
and C from me, he left grade A to buy at the
end. Before he bought grade A, people- you- all you, my creditors,
would have come to Michael, Michael would have said, 'You can't come
to me, you have to go to Dov first, right? He's still
got property in his possession.' Now, why does he have the right
to say that? Why is it that- that- that- that- you guys
come to me first? That was something made to protect Michael's interests,
right? That's completely to protect Michael's interests. People that buy property from
me should not have to have my creditors come to them if
I've got the cash on hand or have property on hand. So
that whole thing that everybody's rights focused on the grade A that
I was left to was based on a institution, on a law
that was instituted to protect Michael's interests. And there- that put all
of you on me and did not let you go to Michael.
And that focused all of your rights on grade A. So Michael
could say, 'In this case, you know what? I waive my- my
rights to that, you know, I waive that law that was done
for my benefit.' Okay, and since if I would imagine that that
law had not existed, then you would not have had prior rights
to grade A, you would have equal- they would have equal rights
to the property he had bought even when he had left grade
A in my possession. Does that- people got that?
Wait, isn't it obvious that if you are the בעל חוב ba'al
chov and you still have property, of course the creditor should come
to you first. Why should I go to somebody else?
I don't know, because you could say it's opposite. You could say
you have a lien on that property, that lien entitles you to
collect that property for payment of debt, why should it matter who's
in possession of that property? As soon as you...
you're the one that owes me money.
I understand.
So the question is, did you view this as a תקנה? takana?
You're right, look, one interesting way the גמרא Gemara conceptualizes this is,
how much do you view my property as a type of a
ערבון, aravon, but fundamentally when you're coming to be paid, you're coming
to me, right? And therefore you only go to my guarantor if
I can't pay. So if we say that's some תקנה takana that
we made to protect Michael, it's in a fundamental principled way you
come to me first. But there is another way of looking at
it, another way of looking at it is, when you borrow money
that gives you rights in my property that can be exercised when
a debt is not paid off, right? So basically look, it's not
personal, it's all business. I lent you money, that gave me rights,
I'm now going to exercise those rights. So it's a different way
of conceptualizing it. But I understand what you're saying. We don't have
to see it as a תקנה takana to protect the person, but
that's how the גמרא Gemara is choosing to see it. If you
see it as a תקנה takana to protect the purchasers, then in
this case the purchaser can say that תקנה takana is working against
my interests, because that תקנה takana would give all of you rights
to Grade A, which I bought at the end. So I'd rather
forget that תקנה takana and therefore you get your normal rights and
they get equally divided between A, B, and C.
The concept of שעבוד shi'abud is that even though you sold it
to somebody else, it's sort of like collecting from you.
Right. Right. And there's a lot of נפקא מינהs nafka mina about
that, about being מוחל mocheil the חוב chov and other types of
things, correct. Okay, so let's take a look.
ופרקינא כדרב אשי. Uparkina k'deRav Ashi. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אלא אימא אמר רב אשי אמרו רבנן אין נפרעין מנכסים
משועבדים במקום שיש בני חורין. Ela eima amar Rav Ashi amru rabanan
ein nifrain minachasim meshuabadin bemakom sheyesh bnei chorin. You cannot collect from
property with liens when there is free property, meaning property in the
possession of the person who owes the money, משום תקנתא דידי, mishum
takanta didi, they were protecting my interest, says Michael who just left.
אנא בהאי תקנתא לא ניחא לי. Ana behai takanta lo nicha li.
Right now I don't want those, I don't want them to protect
my interest. That works against me right now because it focuses all
of you on the Grade A. So we'll pretend that didn't exist
and then your rights are where they naturally would be. כדרבא, Ked'Rava,
like רבא. Rava. דאמר רבא. Damar Rava. Now, because you could say
since when are you allowed to decide, oh, this time it's working
against me, I don't want this הלכה. halacha. So we say no,
actually רבא Rava says you're sometimes allowed to do that. Sometimes the
rabbis make certain תקנות takanos to protect people and they give people
the option of waiving those rights. Okay? And of waiving that תקנה.
takana. Where do we see that?
דאמר רבא כל האומר אי אפשי בתקנת חכמים, Damar Rava kol ha'omer
ee efshi betakanat chachamim, anybody who says, I'm not interested in the
תקנה takana the rabbis made to protect my interest, כגון זו, kegon
zu, like this case, שומעין לו, shomin lo, so you would listen
to him, if it really was a תקנה takana that was totally
just to protect your interests. מאי כגון זו? Mai kegon zu? What
was the case רבא Rava was talking about? כדרב הונא, Ked'Rav Huna,
like רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר רב הונא יכולה אשה שתאמר לבעלה
איני ניזונת ואיני עושה. Damar Rav Huna yechola isha shetomar leva'ala eini
nizonet ve'eini osa.
So the גמרא Gemara says that a woman is... a husband has
to support his wife, provide for her in terms of food and
room and board and the whole thing, and in exchange he gets
her labor. He gets, meaning if she earns some money and
or she does labor in the house, he's entitled to that. So
that was understood, now whose was that benefiting? It was understood that
that was primarily, was it primarily to give the husband the rights
to the wife's labor? No. It was primarily to ensure that the
wife would be supported and protected. In exchange we said, oh, it
will make it... we'll give you something in exchange, you get your
wife's labor, the money that she earns. Fine, but it was all
done to protect her. Let's say she happens to be a corporate
lawyer and making 300, 500 dollars an hour, so she says, this
actually is not working out to my benefit, he's getting all of
my paycheck and I'm just getting him to put some food on
the table. So in this type of a case, I'd rather keep
my own paycheck and he can keep his food. Okay, and so
she's allowed to say that. Okay, so something that was made fundamentally
to protect a certain person's interests, even if there has some type
of a other people benefit type of a thing, some type of
a reciprocal type of a thing, you're allowed to waive, and here
too the person who bought the property is allowed to waive this
תקנה, takana, which so therefore people are not fully focused on Grade
A and they're equally distributed.
This is only for שעבוד, shi'abud, right? Right.
Okay,
now we move on. פשיטא. Pshita. Okay, that was one case that
people bought the property and one guy bought in three separate stages.
Now, מכר לוקח בינונית וזיבורית ושייר עידית לפניו, Machar lokeach beinonit veziborit
veshayer idit lefanav,
so now we're going to... Sort of say, okay, let's go back
to I'm selling my property off. I sold off, and I have
three, these three different categories of people coming against me. So I
sold off my B and C, and I'm left with A, so
then it's like bonanza for everybody, ליתו כולהו וליגבו מעידית, Leitu kulehu
veligbu me-idit,
everybody comes to me because we just said they come to me
first, and everybody gets grade A, דאחרונה היא, de-achrona hi,
that's the last one, ובינונית וזיבורית לית גבי, uveinonit veziborit leit gabei,
and I don't have grade B and C, דמצי למימרא להו גבו
מבינונית וזיבורית, dematzi lemeimra lehu gavu mibeinonit veziborit, them and that they
they
that I could say to them, "Hey, you guys get B and
C," דלא ניחא לי בתקנתא דרבנן, delo nicha li betakanata derabbanan, because
I don't want the תקנתא דרבנן. takanata derabbanan. What do you mean
you don't want the תקנתא דרבנן? takanata derabbanan? The תקנתא דרבנן takanata
derabbanan wasn't to protect me, the תקנתא דרבנן takanata derabbanan was to
protect the person who bought the land. So I can't I can't
it was meant to protect him, so I can't shove them off
on him. So here, I'm the guy who owes the money, I'm
left with A, they all wind up getting A. Okay, so that
would be that's obvious. אבל מכר עידית, Aval machar idit, let's say
I sold A, ושייר בינונית וזיבורית, veshiyyer beinonit veziborit, and I'm left
with B and C. And now I have all three categories coming
to me. Okay, so the בעל חוב baal chov and the כתובת
אשה, kesuvat isha, they're happy, they're getting their B and C. The
נזיקין nezikin guy, he's not happy, he's not getting his A, I
sold off my A. So so what's the story? מאי? Mai? סבר
אביי למימר אתו כולהו גבו מעידית. Sevar Abaye lemeimar atu kulehu gavu
me-idit. Wait a minute, wait, wait, כולהו גבו מעידית? kulehu gavu me-idit?
Wait a minute. מכר עידית ושייר בינונית... Machar idit veshiyyer beinonit... wait
a minute.
Oh
no, no, no, I'm sorry, I said this wrong. The case was
like this, one minute.
Wait, wait, hold on, hold on, a minute.
Oh, I think I said this case wrong. Oh, I'm sorry, I
said this case wrong from the beginning. It's מכר לוקח, Machar lokeach,
I'm sorry. I was too right, right, it was too simple, it
was too simple. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. Let's start off
again. Let's double back. Start off again from the two dots. Because
I'm not the one selling, the guy who bought all three properties
is now selling to another purchaser. I'm sorry, I got it, okay.
Okay, right, right. פשיטא, Pshita, let's go back to the two dots.
מכר לוקח בינונית וזיבורית, Machar lokeach beinonit veziborit, so Michael, who had
bought all three properties, he sold off to a second purchaser B
and C, ושייר עידית לפניו, veshiyyer idit lefanav, and he left A.
ליתו כולהו וליגבו מעידית, Leitu kulehu veligbu me-idit, and everybody comes and
they collect from his A. Why? Because anyway, since he had bought
A last, they should have been entitled to the A. The only
way he got them to not collect from the A was he
said, "I don't need to be protected from the תקנתא דרבנן takanata
derabbanan here," you know, and let's and it's all going to go
back. דאחרונה היא, De-achrona hi, because fundamentally they were anyway entitled to
the A. ובינונית וזיבורית לית גבי, Uveinonit veziborit leit gabei, and in
this case, Michael, who had bought A, B, and C initially, although
he bought A last, he doesn't have B and C, דמצי למימרא
להו גבו מבינונית וזיבורית, dematzi lemeimra lehu gavu mibeinonit veziborit, דלא ניחא
לי בתקנתא דרבנן, delo nicha li betakanata derabbanan, he can't say, "Look,
get B and C, that's what you normally would have gotten, I'm
not interested in the תקנתא דרבנן." takanata derabbanan. You can't waive the
תקנתא דרבנן takanata derabbanan to hurt somebody else. You know, Michael went
ahead and he sold his B and C to Jonathan, Michael can't
say, "Oh, I'm waiving the תקנתא דרבנן takanata derabbanan in my interest,
go collect from Jonathan." No, you can only waive the תקנתא דרבנן,
takanata derabbanan, you know, if you're being impacted, not if it's going
to push it off on him. So therefore, since everybody's rights focused
on A and all he's left with here is A, then they
all get to collect from A. Okay, is that clear? Okay. אבל
מכר עידית ושייר בינונית וזיבורית, Aval machar idit veshiyyer beinonit veziborit, Michael
sold his A to Jonathan. In that case, מאי, mai, what's the
story? Okay, remember, everybody fundamentally started with rights on A, the rights
had focused on A, but Michael was able to distribute it because
he waived the תקנתא דרבנן, takanata derabbanan, but now A has been
passed on to Jonathan. Everybody got the case? Okay, so what's going
to be the story? סבר אביי למימר אתו כולהו גבו מעידית, Sevar
Abaye lemeimar atu kulehu gavu me-idit, let them all get A, they
were all entitled to A, so Michael could have waived that, but
now A has moved on. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, no,
Rava said no. מה מכר ראשון לשני כל זכות שתבא לידו. Ma
machar rishon lesheni kol zechut shetavo leyado. When Michael sold to Jonathan,
he sold, he he gave whatever rights he would have had to
Jonathan, which means when Michael had A, Michael has the ability to
distribute them equally between A, B, and C, right, according to their
categories. So when he, even though he hadn't yet come to court
yet, he hadn't yet waived his rights, he could have done that.
So therefore, since he could have done that, we view it as
though he, what he sold, you know, when he passed it on
to Jonathan, he passed it on with that ability that he himself
would have had, which would have been which would have been to
focus the the נזיקין nezikin guy on A. וכיון דאלו אתו גבי
לוקח ראשון, Vekevan de-ilu atu gabei lokeach rishon, since had they come
to Michael, מצי אגבינהו מבינונית וזיבורית, matzi agbinhu mibeinonit veziborit, he could
have gotten the בעל חוב baal chov and the כתובת אשה kesuvat
isha to get B and C. ואף על גב דכי זבן בינונית
וזיבורית אכתי עידית בני חורין הואי ואין נפרעין מנכסים משועבדים כל זמן
דאיכא בני חורין. V'af al gav d'chi zavan beinonis v'ziboris achti idis
b'nei chorin havai v'ein nifrain mi-nechasim meshuabadim kol zman d'ika b'nei chorin.
But
and even though had, you know, when he bought B and C,
the A was the last property, right? When he had bought B
and C from me, A was my last property,
and everybody's rights had focused on A. ואין נפרעין מנכסים משועבדים כל
זמן דאיכא בני חורין. V'ein nifrain mi-nechasim meshuabadim kol zman d'ika b'nei
chorin. Right? So again, we're reviewing the whole story. It's a little
wordy. Michael bought B and C from me. He could have focused
every, everybody was focused on A because they couldn't collect from Michael
and they could have collected from me. And when even though that's
true, when he bought A from me and they came to him,
מצי אמר להו, matzi amar lehu, he would have said to them,
לא ניחא לי בהאי תקנתא. lo nicha li b'hai takanta. I don't
want this תקנתא takanta that was protecting me and now I'm distributing
you equally between A, B, and C. We're sort of reviewing what
happened in Michael's case. So yes, we were focused on A, but
then once Michael got A and because it was all done to
protect him, he can now redistribute us to A, B, and C.
So once that's true, לוקח שני נמי, lokeiach sheni nami, so when
he passes on to Jonathan, Jonathan can say, מצי אמר להו, matzi
amar lehu, גבי בינונית וזיבורית. gabi beinonis v'ziboris. You know what? You
other two guys, בעל חוב, baal chov, כתובת אישה, kesubas isha, you
go back to Michael and you get your B and C there.
דכי זבן לוקח שני אדעתא דכל זכותא דהוה ליה לראשון בגווה זבן,
D'chi zavan lokeiach sheni adaata d'kol zchusa d'hava lei l'rishon b'gavah zavan,
cause when Jonathan bought from Michael, he bought it with the same
rights, you know, with the same power that Michael had to decline
the תקנתא. takanta. Like basically since Michael could have distributed it that
way and limited just the נזיקין Nezikin guy to A, when Michael
bought A he was buying it only with the נזיקין Nezikin person,
you know, lien on it and not everybody else's. Okay.
Now he only owns A, he's declining the תקנתא takanta and reverting
the חוב chov back to the guy who has the lien.
You're not declining the תקנתא, takanta, Michael because he could have declined
the תקנתא takanta and could have distributed everybody equally, you view it
as if he had done that. Okay. And therefore when he sold
you A, he sold you A only with the lien of the
נזיקין Nezikin and not with everybody's lien. When A, B, and C
were in Michael's possessions, he had the ability to redistribute the liens
away from A and equally between A, B, and
C. Right? Everybody got that? He could have waved the תקנתא takanta
and distributed it. So since he could have and that obviously would
have been in his best interest, we view it essentially as if
he did that. So when he sold you A, he sold you
A only with the lien of the נזיקין Nezikin and not with
everybody's lien on A.
If he sells you A with the right for you to decline,
he sells you A with the understanding that it was declined.
Exactly, exactly. As if he had already declined. Right. That's the way
I would phrase it. Okay. So I mean the language of the
גמרא Gemara might sort of say it gives you that right, but
I would phrase it as we view it as though it's already
sort of, you know, done in the best way possible and therefore
you, it's as if it's already been declined.
It can be viewed the other way.
Yeah, exactly. Okay. So we'll end with this and pick up with
another case tomorrow.
See, the נזיקין Nezikin guy had, he has a lien on the.